Welcome to
Good morning, church.
Thank you all so much for joining.
Morning, Sherry.
I love the energy.
Let's go.
Thanks so much for joining us this morning.
We are continuing our series, long series, through the summer.
I know all of you, you haven't missed a single week for vacation.
None of you have gone anywhere nicer than where I've gone.
It's fine.
None of you are watching online from the beach.
I'm not envious or jealous or anything.
Long summer series, through the life and ministry and teachings of the Apostle Paul.
And our desire is that as we continue this series, that we would better understand who
Paul is because he is the writer of a majority of the New Testament.
So that as we read through his letters, we can better understand the context, the story
behind the author that God chose by the power of his spirit to breathe through so much of
our New Testament Scriptures.
We looked at the biography of his life.
He started a persecutor of the church.
He started hating the church and had a radical encounter with Jesus, which led him into a deep,
deep relationship with the Lord that fueled a passion for the church.
He went on missionary journeys to plant and to strengthen churches.
And ultimately, he went on a missionary journey at the end of his life where he voluntarily went
to prison so that he could get to Rome to share the gospel with those who might not
hear it otherwise.
He sacrificed his entire life for the gospel of Jesus.
We looked at his biography.
And last week, we started, we're going to go through about the next four weeks, pastoral
kind of teachings and contributions that he made to the church.
And we started last week by saying what Paul, how Paul talked about living missionally, living
towards people who are outside the family of God, people who aren't yet brought into the
family of God, who haven't yet submitted their lives to Jesus.
And we said that Paul's, his whole method for living missionally was to lay down his priorities,
his privileges, and his propensities to win an argument in order to win a person.
Like he laid it all down.
Everything that he had, everything that he was able to claim, he said, none of it is worth
the person who is outside the family of God.
We will lay it all down.
He calls, he invites all of us to do that, to live in a way that invites people into a right
relationship with God.
And this week, we're going to look at a natural consequence of what happens when we are successful
at this.
Like when we are successful at reaching people who are outside the family of God and bringing
them inside the family of God, people from different ethnicities, different backgrounds,
different theologies, different ideologies.
Like when we reach a diverse group of people, guess what the church typically has a problem
with next?
Unity.
Right?
We struggle with unity as we reach a diverse background of people because we're good with
people that look like us, talk like us, act like us, all of that.
Right?
But if we do what Paul calls us to do, if we lay down our priorities and privileges and propensities
to win arguments, we will win people who disagree with us on major consequential issues.
And yet Paul, throughout his writings, is constantly hammering home the importance of the church
being unified.
It's one of the last things that Jesus prayed before he went to the cross, that the world
will know that we are his disciples by our love for one another.
And yet we struggle with this as people come into the family of God that look different than
us.
And so, we talked about living missionally.
This week, we're going to talk about how do we have unity as we reach people who are far
from God.
Sound like a plan?
All right, let's pray.
Holy Spirit, we invite you into this place.
We know that you have been this week preparing all of us to hear and to receive, not just the
message from stage, but through the worship and through interactions and prayers in the
lobby and in this place.
God, we know that you have a desire to conform us into your image, to conform us to the image
of Jesus.
We want this hour to do that in some way, shape, or form.
We believe that you will do that.
We're inviting you to do that.
May we not have hard hearts, not have dull ears.
May we open ourselves up before you.
May you transform us from the inside out, not some kind of religious checkbox where we
just do the things that you say to do begrudgingly, but may you give us the deep, deep desire to
find unity with our brothers and sisters that we disagree with on difficult issues.
God, we believe that your church is most effective.
I believe that your church is most effective when we are most unified.
And I believe that we have the temptation, the struggle to not pursue that.
So may this morning be a great reminder.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you have Bibles, I'd love for you to turn to Romans chapter 14.
If you have a phone app or whatever, Romans chapter 14.
I'm going to be reading from the ESV in a little bit so that you can follow along with
me, one of the biggest privileges I get to participate in as a pastor is something that is called premarital
counseling.
Any of you ever experienced premarital counseling?
Some of you?
All right.
I'm not making eye contact with the couple in the front row who is currently in premarital
counseling with me.
Don't worry.
What's shared in premarital counseling stays in premarital counseling.
This will not be any of your stories.
Probably.
No, I'm just kidding.
But here's the thing about premarital counseling, where I often start with in premarital counseling
is I often ask people, like, what were the cultural norms in your family?
How did things operate in your family of origin?
And then identify which of those things do you like, dislike, agree with, want to stay the
same, want to change?
And it's important that we have these dialogues because we all have norms in our family.
Whether you know it or not, there is a normal experience for your family.
And oftentimes when two people come together from different families, they are on a crash
course to realize that what they thought was normal to them wasn't necessarily normal to
the other person.
Does that make sense?
One of my favorite, like, little examples of this is maybe you grew up in a home where
the norm was if you did the cooking, you don't do the dishes.
That's, like, somewhat normal for some families, right?
Now, if I don't find ways to forge those conversations with a young couple before they get married,
if that was not the norm for the young man in the house, and the new lovely wife cooks dinner,
wonderful dinner, and the man enjoys it and sits down on the couch and props his feet up,
and for the wife, the norm was, I'm not doing the dishes.
That man is on a collision course for conflict, right?
And this is, like, this is a small illustration of what happens on such a bigger scale
when we reach diverse people coming into the family of God, because the church is the family of God.
And as people come in with diverse backgrounds, diverse experiences, ideological thoughts,
different worldviews, all of that stuff, we're all submitted to the Lord Jesus, but we don't become
the same overnight, right?
And so what happens in the church is we come into this place, we reach people who are different than us,
and we immediately find tension.
We find conflict because somebody sitting next to us thinks something differently than we do,
or they see something from a different perspective than we do, and we say, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
That's not how this thing works.
This is how this thing works.
And so we end up fighting over things that we shouldn't be fighting over.
We end up getting confused over things that shouldn't be confusing,
because we're fixated on things that are less important than the fact that we've all submitted
to Jesus as Lord.
And so we want to pursue unity.
We want to have intentional conversations about our perspectives and our backgrounds.
I love Austin Fisher as a pastor I really admire, and he says this,
the church at its best is the most unifying social organization in world history.
Notice he says, at its best.
This is what Christ intended.
When he prayed, you will be one.
The world will know that you are my disciples when you are one.
The church at its best is the most unifying social organization in world history,
and yet as we look throughout church history,
we see divisions and denominations and splits over and over and over again.
And I think it's possible that we're missing out on the fullness of what God has for his church.
And so in our passage today, we're going to look at a central part of Paul's teaching
to a diverse and divided church.
The church at Rome was full of Jews and Gentiles from different backgrounds
and different ideologies and different socioeconomic statuses,
and they were having trouble finding unity.
They were getting in conflicts over things that to us will look silly,
but to them very much were not silly.
So before we jump specifically into the passage of Romans 14,
I want to do a quick 30,000-foot overview of the entire book of Romans
so we don't miss Paul's overarching point.
I like to imagine, especially because we're going to be taking communion at the end of service,
I like to imagine that the book of Romans was written to a group of diverse,
divided Christians around a dinner table with Jesus at the head of the table.
This is God's image for the church.
We are all supposed to be sitting around one table with Jesus at the head.
In Romans 1-11, the first half of Romans, Paul says,
look to Jesus at the head of the table.
Remember who he is, what he is like, and why he invited you to the table in the first place,
how you got there.
Romans 1-11 is all about looking to Jesus at the head of the table.
He has brought you into the family of God,
not by works, but by faith in the Lord Jesus.
No matter what background you come from, slave, free, Jew, Gentile,
he has brought, he has invited all of us to sit at the same table by faith in the Lord Jesus.
Look to Jesus at the head of the table.
That's the first section of Romans.
And then he says, okay, now with that in mind,
with that vision of you looking to Jesus at the head of the table,
now look around at one another.
With the same perspective that Jesus looks at you,
look to one another with the same eyes that Jesus looks to you.
And Paul believes that a right understanding of who God is
will lead us to a right relationship with one another.
Pretty simple concept, right?
The book of Romans is not that hard to understand.
However, much of the American church,
we love to study the theology found in Romans.
But we often lose sight of why Paul is going so depth in the theology in the first place.
Unity.
And instead of walking away with Paul's intended vision,
we often walk away more divided than ever
because we just get in fights over what chapters 1 through 11 say
without ever getting to the application of chapters 12 through 16.
There's actually a scholar that I love.
If you ever get the chance to read a book by Scott McKnight,
I'd encourage you to do so.
Scott McKnight just recently wrote a book called
Reading Romans Backward.
And his whole point is that the theology that Paul lays out in 1 through 11,
the whole point of the theology in 1 through 11
is to give a foundation for the application in chapters 12 through 16.
So he says, if you start by reading 12 through 16,
understanding what Paul's actually trying to communicate in his theology,
then we will be less tempted to miss the mark.
But instead, we get so fixated on the beauty, the depth, the theology in 1 through 11,
and we just like, oh yeah, we'll get to 12 through 16 later.
But the whole point of Paul writing the book of Romans
was the application in 12 through 16.
The whole reason he slaved on the letter to Romans
was so that this divided group of believers would be united.
And somehow, we read this book and walk away more divided than ever.
Scott summarizes his point here.
He says,
Paul's mission was to establish churches in the Roman Empire
made up of Jews and Gentiles, slaves and free, male and female.
His fear was denominations, one Jewish, one Gentile.
And his message was peace.
This is the point of the book of Romans,
that we would be united in the midst of our consequential differences.
It's not that the things that we divide over don't matter.
It's that they don't matter as much as unity.
I know brothers and sisters that I love and I'm thankful for
who literally, they have a master's degree on Romans 1 through 11.
But if you look at the way that they treat one another around the table,
you would never know that they've even read 12 through 16.
And I know brothers and sisters who are the most kind, compassionate, and loving people
who are obsessed with the commands in chapters 12 through 16.
They're obsessed with the idea about loving people well.
But they don't take enough time to look at Jesus at the head of the table
and they end up loving people in a way that doesn't actually mirror the love of Jesus.
It's a surface level, superficial type of love for one another that isn't rooted in who Jesus is.
And others, this is the most heartbreaking version,
others are content to leave the table where Jesus is at the head
and start their own little table full of people that look exactly like them,
talk exactly like them, act exactly like them,
and believe exactly like them.
Listen to this, this is going to be hard for us to hear
because the command to love your neighbor as yourself
is a lot easier when your neighbor looks exactly like you.
In all three of these approaches to the letter of Romans,
Paul would likely roll his eyes at
because his point is that we would all come around the table
together with Jesus at the head,
that we would look to him,
let him define what love is,
let him define what truth is,
let him define where salvation is found,
and then we would look to one another
and we would lock arms and find unity
in the midst of our diverse opinions over consequential matters.
Does that make sense?
All right, so let's dive into the specific text
where Paul is going to address a few arguments
that are happening in the Roman church.
We'll just read it and then we'll kind of unpack it as we go.
Romans chapter 14, starting in verse 1,
we'll read through verse 12.
Paul says,
I let you guys off on that.
Let's go back.
You guys didn't participate at all.
I'm just going to breeze past like you guys did it,
but you didn't do it.
All right, we're going to get back.
We're going to read again,
and when we get to opinions,
everybody say it with me.
As for the one who is weak in faith,
welcome him,
but not to quarrel over opinions.
Thank you.
One person believes he may eat anything
while the weak person eats only vegetables.
Any vegetarians in the room?
I'm kidding.
Let not the one who eats despise the one who abstains,
and let not the one who abstains
pass judgment on the one who eats,
for God has welcomed him.
Who are you to pass judgment on the servant of another?
It is before his own master that he stands or falls,
and he will be upheld,
for the Lord is able to make him stand.
One person esteems one day as better than another,
while another esteems all days alike.
Each one should be fully convinced in his own mind
that the one who observes the day
observes it in honor of the Lord.
The one who eats,
eats in honor of the Lord,
since he gives thanks to God,
while the one who abstains,
abstains in honor of the Lord
and gives thanks to God.
For none of us lives to himself,
and none of us will die to himself.
For if we live,
we live to the Lord,
and if we die,
we die to the Lord.
So then,
whether we live
or whether we die,
we are the Lord's.
For to this end,
Christ died and lived again.
This is the whole point.
The whole reason Jesus came,
that he might be both
Lord of the living and the dead.
Why do we pass judgment on our brothers?
Or you,
why do you despise your brother?
For we will stand before the judgment seat of Christ,
for it is written,
As I live,
says the Lord,
every knee shall bow
and every tongue shall confess to God.
So then,
each of us will give an account to God.
This is the word of the Lord.
We're getting there.
Love it.
So,
Paul here is addressing
two groups of Christians
who have become both
either judgmental
or hateful
towards one another
over differences of opinion
about how to live out
the Christian life.
How do we apply the message
that Jesus is Lord of our lives?
And it's important
that we distinguish this morning,
we are talking about
what the NIV translates,
disputable matters.
The ESV translated,
opinions.
Right?
We are not talking about
the doctrines of the gospel,
the things that we cannot divide over.
We're talking about opinions,
disputable matters.
And what happens in the church
is we struggle to figure out
who gets to define
what's an opinion
and what's not an opinion,
what's a disputable matter
and what's not a disputable matter.
Paul says in 1 Corinthians 15,
these are the non-disputable things.
He says,
I passed on to you
what was most important.
This is what we cannot divide over.
This is what we cannot water down.
What has also been passed on to me
that Christ died for our sins
just as the Scripture says,
that he was buried,
that he was raised from the dead
on the third day
just as the Scripture said.
Jesus is the Son of God.
He lived a perfect life.
He died on the cross
to restore us
into right relationship with God.
These are non-negotiables.
You don't get to have
an opinion about this
if you want to be welcomed
into the family of God
as a brother and sister.
This is family stuff.
If we are in the family of God,
we submit to the lordship of Jesus.
All of these things
are non-negotiable,
but pretty much everything
after that
is a disputable matter.
But here's one more
non-negotiable.
One more non-negotiable
is unity, right?
Unity is a non-negotiable,
and unfortunately,
we, many of us in the church,
we have made unity
a negotiable issue
because we have made
other negotiable issues
non-negotiable.
Does that make sense?
We have taken opinions
that are negotiable,
and we said,
here, this list of opinions,
let me put it on a document.
Let me put it in a constitution.
Let me put it on a creed.
These opinions that I have
about God
and how people should live
in accordance with God,
these are non-negotiable,
and therefore,
I'm going to break unity
with these other brothers
and sisters
who are submitted
to the lordship of Jesus
who believe
all of the non-negotiables
and we say,
I can't have unity
with that person,
and it's so frustrating
because unity
is a non-negotiable,
and some of the things
we break unity over
are negotiable.
So, Paul here,
he's addressing this issue.
He's saying,
you're making too many things
non-negotiables.
You're making opinionated matters
non-opinionated matters,
and you're losing sight
of the whole point
of why Jesus brought you together
in the first place.
Now,
at a surface level reading
thousands of years
removed from the culture,
these arguments
seem pretty petty
and foolish,
right?
Eating vegetables,
not eating vegetables,
what day of the week
you do certain things.
Seems like a petty argument,
but these were anything
but that
for the Roman church.
The food that they felt
comfortable
or not comfortable eating,
the holidays
that they thought
should be
or shouldn't be celebrated
or ignored
were highly emotionally
charged issues.
These were not
silly disagreements
for them.
And I've heard
a lot of pastors
preach this passage
and they apply it
to really silly disagreements.
And I think
that's the worst thing
that we can do
to this passage
is this is not
carpet color level
disagreements,
right?
This is not the church
dividing over what color
the carpet is.
Although churches
have done that
in the past
and if you're
in that mindset
send me an email
I'll send you
a list of churches
that I would love
for you to try out.
Right?
I'm kidding
because now I'm convicted
because unity.
All right.
That's why we don't
have carpet.
Exactly.
There's no color
to choose.
But here's the worst
thing we could do
is underestimate
how important
these issues were
to these individuals
as we apply
the principles
to our lives.
These were emotionally
charged issues.
These issues
for us
are probably
more like
who should a Christian
vote for?
Should Christians
vote at all?
How should Christians
think about military
service or self-defense?
What is your position
on the war,
the conflict
in Israel-Palestine?
Should Christians
partake in things
like alcohol
or THC?
What level
of leadership
should women
have in the church?
What mode
of baptism
should we perform?
Is there a rapture
or is there not
a rapture?
And if there is,
when is it going
to happen?
And on and on
the list goes,
right?
There are tons
of things
that we as Christians
have opinions over
and I'm not saying
that these things
don't matter.
They matter a lot
but they matter
less than unity
under the lordship
of Jesus.
I think a good test
for you to decide
what level
or what things
are you struggling
with that are opinions
is if you've ever
found yourself saying
how in the world
could a good Christian
think blank?
How in the world
could a good Christian
vote for blank?
How in the world
could a good Christian
go to a church
that blank?
These are the type
of issues
that we're talking
about here.
And this is what
each of the two groups
in this passage
were thinking about.
They were both
looking at each other
and saying
how in the world
could a good Christian
eat that meat
sacrificed to idols?
How in the world
could a good Christian
go to Sabbath
on Sunday
or Saturday?
How in the world
could a good Christian
participate in this
pagan Roman holiday?
How in the world
could a good Christian
continue to
participate in these
Jewish holidays
that were all
just a shadow
of Jesus
and now that
Jesus has come
they don't matter.
Right?
These were highly
emotionally charged
issues.
I love how
Austin Fisher
puts this.
I'll quote him again.
He says,
I'm not saying
all of our differences
are inconsequential.
Some of them
are very consequential.
But if Jesus
only holds us together
in inconsequential
differences
that's not very
impressive.
Back to our table
where we all
look alike, right?
If the church
of Jesus Christ
is only unifying
people that all
pretty much
look alike,
think alike,
vote alike,
agree with everything
they all agree with,
then how is the world
going to look at that
and say,
wow, you guys
are doing something
special.
Right?
No, the reason
that Jesus said
the way the world
will know
that you are my
disciples
is by your love
for one another
is because
male and female,
slave and free,
Jew and Gentile,
all of these
incredibly diverse
people with
incredibly different
opinions about
consequential matters
were able to
lay down those
consequential matters
in order to unite
for the fact
that Jesus is Lord,
he's the hope
of the world
and nothing else
matters more than that.
So I'm not saying
these things
aren't important
and that we shouldn't
have conversations
about them,
but what I'm saying
is if they get
in the way
of our unity,
we've missed
the point
all together.
So Paul makes
very clear,
he's talking about
opinions,
disputable matters,
there are things
that we will
separate over,
there are things
that matter so much
that we have
to fight for them
and there are
other things
that we can have
a multitude
of opinions about.
Another thing
I want to clarify
here is that
Paul has two
categories of
people in mind,
he talks about
the strong
and the weak,
a couple clarifying
points and then
we'll hop into
what that means,
what believers
were strong,
were weak
and why.
The first point
I'd like to make
is that all of us
are probably strong
in some areas
and weak
in others
and the second
is that Paul
is less concerned
with who is right
and more concerned
with awareness.
He kind of identifies
himself in one
of the categories
but he's not saying
man,
if you're strong
you're better
than the weak,
if you're weak
you're better
than the strong,
he's just saying
look,
we have categories
of people
that have different
levels of faith
when it comes
to living out
these disputable
matters
and the best
thing that you
can do for yourself
and for those
around you
is to figure out
where you're at
in that category
to identify yourself
to know yourself
to know your brother
and sister
so that you can
better relate
to one another
the whole point
of even making
these categories
was so that we
can better relate
to one another
does that make sense?
Alright,
I made a chart
to try and explain
the weak
and the strong
I hope that this
is helpful
it's a man-made chart
it's got
it's weaknesses
it's got its flaws
but I think
it's helpful
essentially
what Paul
is saying here
is there's two
different ways
that you can end
up separating
yourself from
communion with God
you've got
sin, right?
there's a line
in which God
says this is right
and this is wrong
if you do this
it's wrong
and the strong
believers
they're able
to kind of
go all the way
up to the line
of sin
and live
in the freedom
of Christ
and go to church
on a Thursday night
rather than a Sunday
they're able
to like
there's gray
involved
in following
Jesus
on the strong
side
and they can
kind of get
all the way
up to the line
to rebellion
now
there's another
version of
separating from
God altogether
on the more
conservative side
on the religious
side
and the weak
tend to gravitate
towards that side
of religion
where
if they're not
careful
they can end up
just following
a list of rules
and requirements
black and white
lists
and they end up
missing God
all of together
and Paul is saying
both sides
like there's
a certain level
where you can go
too far
on both sides
and he's saying
but if you're
in the middle
if you're in this
part where you're
pursuing God
you're finding
right relationship
with God
that it's okay
to be on either
side
just be aware
of what side
you're on
and aware
of the way
that that impacts
your relationship
with others
the strong
they can explore
their freedom
in Christ
without sin
they understand
the nuance
and the beauty
of the kingdom
of God
and they are
comfortable
with gray
some of us
in the room
are black and white
people
we are like
no thank you
just tell me
what's right
tell me what's wrong
I don't want
no gray for me
and that's okay
that's not necessarily
a bad thing
the weak
they need to stay
far away
from the line
of sin
to avoid
their conscience
being violated
they are much
more comfortable
with the black
and the white
they are much
more comfortable
with a list
of things
that they should
do
and they shouldn't
does that make sense
so these are the two
categories of people
that we're talking
about
and what we're
going to find out
is even though
both categories
are fine
oftentimes they're
living in this good
space where they're
being obedient to God
they're doing the
things that God's
called them to do
we can go too far
on the strong side
on the weak side
but Paul is addressing
these two categories
of people
they're living
in God's will
he's going to say
later
they're both
doing the things
that they're doing
in order to honor God
so if you're doing
that you're great
you're living
in a safe space
but you've got
to be aware
of your propensity
you've got to be aware
that you're more
comfortable living
in gray
and when you come
across a brother
or sister
who needs more
black and white
then you have
compassion for them
you lay down
your preferences
your priorities
and your propensity
to win an argument
in order to
love that person
well
sometimes you submit
to their rules
and their regulations
so that you don't
break fellowship
with them
because this whole
thing is about unity
so real quick
let me give some
practical examples
of where I think
I'm probably strong
and weak
just so that you can
see how this plays out
and maybe you can
begin to think about
areas of your life
where you're strong
or you're weak
I think it's helpful
first
I think personally
and maybe it's
self-serving to say
this on a message
on unity
but I think I have
strength in the area
of unity
where I can worship
with learn from
read books
from scholars
and authors
and pastors
who I agree
or disagree with
on a number
of things
it does not make
me uncomfortable
to read a commentary
from a pastor
who I disagree
with 90%
of their theology
but they're
a follower of Jesus
they love the Lord
I can live in that space
right
does not make me
uncomfortable
does not violate
my conscience
now I am
extremely weak
when it comes
to political matters
extremely weak
I don't even want
to go near it
because I know
my heart
and what it means
for me is
often I abstain
from voting
altogether
I refuse to say
the pledge of allegiance
I don't even
really like standing
for the national anthem
and that is not
because those things
are wrong
for certain people
it's because
I know my heart
I know my propensity
to over idolize
the nation state
to put my hope
in the government
to think that
the government
is going to solve
all of my problems
that is an area
that I am extremely
weak in
and so I run
to rules
I create rules
for myself
because I know
what can happen
and many of you
you stand
for the pledge
of allegiance
you say
or you stand
for the national anthem
you say the pledge
of allegiance
and you do so
in good conscience
honoring the Lord
and I am not
saying that
you are wrong
and I am right
I am saying
I am weak
and you are strong
does that make sense
okay
so now that we got
the two categories
we understand
we're talking about
strong and weak
but they're all
living in
a desire
to obey
the Lord
and they're doing it
on matters
that are disputable
they're having
these emotionally
charged arguments
and Paul gives
two principles
to help them
stay rooted
in unity
in the midst
of disagreements
principle number
one is this
it's found
in verses
one through four
Paul says
accept one another
as family
because God
in Christ
accepts you
accept one another
welcome one another
as family
because that's
what God
has done
for you
ask for the one
who is weak
in faith
welcome him
don't quarrel
over opinions
one person
believes one thing
another
believes another
who are you
to pass judgment
on the servant
of another
it is before
his own master
that he stands
or he falls
and he will be
upheld
for the Lord
will make him
stand
every individual
who submitted
their lives
to Jesus
as Lord
has been accepted
into God's family
we are all
members of Christ's body
adopted
into the same family
and we are going
to spend eternity
together
so we better
figure out
how to get along
now
Paul says
look to the head
of the table
remember
when you are lost
in sin
and brokenness
remember that
Christ invited you
to become a part
of his table
freely
through his death
and resurrection
on the cross
remember that
he just told you
to come as you are
you're accepted
you're loved
you are brought
into the family
of God
look to the head
of the table
and remember
that he invited
everyone who sits
beside you
the same way
that he invited
you
they are
welcomed
fully loved
fully accepted
now
this seems like
a basic enough
principle
shouldn't really
struggle to apply
it that much
right
it's a basic
principle
but we are
broken
selfish
prideful
and opinionated
people
we might agree
with this statement
intellectually
until another
Christian
has a different
opinion
on one
of our
how
could a
good
Christian
ever
do
blank
and then
all of a sudden
you're like
you want me
to accept
that person
into my
family
anybody
have any
crazy
uncles
at the
4th of July
picnic
this week
right
this is an
earthly
illustration
of that
like
they're
family
welcome
at the
4th of July
picnic
even if
they're
a little
wonky
on some
stuff
they're
family
this is
what Paul
says
about
everyone
who has
submitted
their lives
to the
lordship
of Jesus
they're
family
God
has
accepted
them
and so
you
should
accept
them
but
we
struggle
with
this
as I
was
studying
for
this
sermon
I
came
across
a
beautiful
illustration
well
it's
actually
a
really
sad
illustration
but
it
illustrates
this
point
really
well
that
we
agree
with
this
intellectually
but
when
it
comes
to
living
it
out
we
struggle
with
it
so
Charles
Spurgeon
famous
preacher
in
London
incredible
ministry
many of
you have
probably
read
some
of
his
sermons
I
came
across
this
quote
in
a
commentary
that I
read
about
this
passage
is
what
Charles
Spurgeon
says
about
this
idea
of
accepting
one
another
as
family
because
God
has
accepted
us
he
says
this
the
term
Jesus
our
Lord
seems
to
draw
a
circle
around
all
the
elect
of
God
the
whole
host
of
the
redeemed
out
of
every
nation
kindred
and
tribe
tongue
and
people
in
every
land
and
every
age
it
seems
to
remind
me
of
a
kind
of
clanship
which
exists
among
all
believers
just
as
the
old
highland
clansmen
when
they
saw
the
head
of
the
clan
all
felt
intense
enthusiasm
at
the
sight
great
center
and
meeting
place
for
all
the
diverse
families
in
the
clan
he's
saying
that
is
Jesus
for
those
of
us
who
have
submitted
to
him
as
Lord
Jesus
is
the
great
center
the
one
who
brings
us
all
together
in
the
midst
of
our
diversity
and
with
him
leading
them
they
rushed
forward
to
victory
over
death
victory
or
death
with
the
utmost
enthusiasm
so
when
your
Lord
is
my
Lord
so
we
are
brothers
and
sisters
in
him
and
we
clasp
hands
around
him
and
say
Jesus
our
Lord
pretty
good
stuff
right
pretty
good
stuff
now
I
read
that
quote
in
one
commentary
and
then
a
couple
days
later
I
came
across
the
story
where
my
guy
Charles
good
dude
gets
it
preached
a
great
sermon
about
unity
Spurgeon
preaches
this
powerful
message
on
unity
in
the
midst
of
consequential
differences
and
yet
I
came
across
a
story
where
the
second
most
famous
preacher
in
London
alongside
of
Charles
Spurgeon
they were
good
pals
for a
while
they
swapped
pulpits
they
worked
together
in
ministry
but
later
in
their
ministry
Spurgeon
decided
that
he
could
no
longer
have
fellowship
with
this
other
pastor
because
this
man
had
the
audacity
to
go
the
theater
can
you
believe
that
he
went
to
the
theater
and
Spurgeon
said
all
of
this
beautiful
stuff
about
Jesus
is
Lord
and
we're
all
clasping
hands
together
except
for
you
sir
because
you
go
to
the
theater
so
you
are
not
welcome
in
my
family
right
don't
we
do
this
I'm
not
throwing
shade
at
Charles
Spurgeon
he's
dead
already
he's
going
to
stand
before
the
Lord
for
judgment
it's
not
does
something
that
we
don't
like
and
all
of
a
sudden
it's
like
unity
is
important
theater
right
unity
is
important
but
you
voted
for
Donald
Trump
I'm
going
to
the
other
side
unity
is
important
but
you
voted
for
Joe
Biden
right
like
whatever
the
thing
is
I'm
using
this
because
November
is
coming
and
we've
got
to
ground
ourselves
in
this
conversation
before
it
happens
that
unity
is
really
important
but
Charles
Spurgeon
preached
an
incredible
sermon
on
unity
and
then
said
you
go
to
the
theater
dude
can't
hang
out
with
you
now
guess
what
his
brother
who
he
persecuted
for
going
to
the
theater
of
course
that
guy
was
super
godly
I'm
sure
he
was
strong
and
he
said
you
know
what
I
forgive
you
no
know
what
he
said
Spurgeon
you
smoke
cigars
I
don't
want
to
have
fellowship
with
you
anyway
so
Spurgeon
is
like
dude
you
go
to
the
theater
our
churches
can't
hang
out
we
can't
serve
one
another
anymore
And he's like, well, fine, you smoke cigars.
That makes you a terrible person too.
It's funny until we do the same thing with our own version of that conversation, right?
Listen to Paul's diagnosis of how this plays itself out between the strong and the weak.
It's exactly what happened with Spurgeon and his fellow pastors.
It's exactly what happens with you and I.
Let not the one who eats despise the one who abstains.
Let not the one who abstains pass judgment on the one who eats, for God has welcomed him.
He says, the temptation for the strong is to hate the weak.
You rule followers, you black and white list makers, you guys are just annoying us.
You're making everything harder than it has to be.
Leave us alone and let us live in the gray.
You guys go sit at your own table in the black and white.
You guys are so frustrated.
The black and white are like, you guys don't obey anything God tells you to obey.
You don't care about any of the rules or any of the regulations.
You make up your own stuff.
You do whatever you want to do, right?
Hatred towards the weak.
Judgmental towards the strong.
How accurate is Paul's diagnosis of the human heart?
The strong will despise the weak.
The weak will become judgmental of the strong.
And both responses break the heart of God.
Paul's response to both is, the Lord will uphold your brother and your sister.
I love this.
Listen to this at the end of verse four.
Who are we to pass judgment on the servant of another?
It is before his own master that he stands or falls.
And he will be upheld for the Lord is able to make him stand.
See, we justify these disagreements.
We justify this disunity because we say it's for their own good.
We're trying to make sure they don't fall.
They're going to fall into sin.
They're going to fall into religion.
They're going to fall.
We have to do something about this.
And Paul says, let God parent his children.
Let God do it.
You're not going to make anybody stand or anybody.
Well, you can make people fall.
But he says, look, the Lord will hold them up.
I only got one kid right now, but I imagine parenting multiple children is a bit more nuanced
than parenting one child.
I imagine that if the Lord blesses me with a second child, that I am not going to parent
that child exactly the way that I parent Rory because they're two unique individuals with
unique backgrounds, with unique DNA, like, right?
And Paul's saying here, let God parent his kids.
Don't break fellowship with your siblings because you think they should live like you
and they think you should live like them.
It's actually so much better for the family of God that we live together in the midst of
difficult disagreements and unity.
We all grow.
We all conform to the image of Jesus as we learn from one another.
Make sense?
All right.
Second principle.
I didn't even give you time to answer that.
I just assumed that it made sense, but we're going on.
Number two, don't judge one another because God will judge you both.
Now, it's important before we go on that I say we're talking about disputable matters.
There are times in which we are called to lovingly bring judgment to our brothers and sisters if
they are living in open, unrepentant sin.
We're going to talk about that next week.
We don't have time for that this week.
So, disputable matters, do not judge one another because God will judge you both.
Verse 5.
One person that seems one day is better than another, while another seems all days alike.
Each one should be fully convinced in his own mind.
Listen to this.
This is beautiful.
Paul says,
Isn't that beautiful?
Paul's point in this section is that both groups believe what they believe and are doing
what they are doing in order to honor the Lord.
Their motivations are pure and right.
Both the weak and the strong are making the decisions they're making.
They're having the opinions that they have in order to honor God.
And both of them are going to stand before God one day and give an account for the decisions
that they made.
And both of them are probably going to be wrong on some of the decisions that they made.
And God, who is our loving Father and just judge, will work all of that out in the end.
It is not our job to figure that out here.
We're all going to be lovingly corrected by Jesus on disputable matters.
So let's spend time allowing him to search our hearts and reveal where we are getting things wrong.
The less time you spend correcting others, the more time you have to allow Jesus to correct you.
And the closer we will all get to the heart of the Father.
But I think one of the reasons we struggle with this is, I don't think any of you are like this.
It's just me.
I believe the best about my motivations, and I assume the worst about the motivations of those who are doing something different than me.
Thanks.
Appreciate that.
Right?
It's like, no, I'm doing, I'm not doing the thing because my heart's in the right place.
So therefore, they must be doing the thing because their heart's in the wrong place.
And Paul here is very clear in this passage.
Both of them have their hearts in the right place.
Both groups are doing what they're doing to honor God.
And we miss this over and over and over again.
All right.
I don't have time for that.
Okay.
So as we begin to kind of land the plane, you guys are going to be proud of me.
I withheld some things there.
All right.
I never do that.
I'm proud of myself.
Okay.
Let's go.
Pound the back.
Okay.
As we begin to land the plane, I want to quickly share five lies that I believe the enemy uses to cause the church to divide over disputable matters.
And full disclosure, I stole this from another pastor, but it was too good not to share.
Okay.
Number one, we confuse unity with uniformity.
We confuse unity with uniformity.
We want, in order for unity to happen, we want everybody to believe exactly what we believe, to make the same decisions about disputable matters that we make.
And we think, well, if they're different than us, then one of us has to be wrong.
And this passage very clearly says, no, you can both be right.
You can both honor God in your convictions on matters of opinion.
And it's actually better that you live together in the same space.
You make each other better.
These arguments done in a respectful and helpful way make the body of Christ better.
Second, we bind others by our conscience.
We have heard from the Lord something that is clear for us to do or not do.
Right?
Let's go back to the politics thing.
Like, the worst thing that I could do as a weak brother when it comes to politics is tell everybody else they have to live by my conviction.
I can tell you why I had that conviction.
I can argue with you.
I can give you argumental points about why I have come to this conclusion.
But if I say, you have to do everything the way that I do it or else you're sinning, I'm making myself judge and juror.
And I'm eliminating God from the process.
Don't bind others by your conscience.
You work out your conscience with the Lord in prayer.
And you have conversations with your brothers and sisters who are coming to different conclusions.
And you fight for unity in the midst of deep conflict on disputable matters.
Third, our preferences become our prejudices.
This one hurts.
We often choose where we go to church far more based on our preferences than anything else.
But we don't even acknowledge them as preferences.
We acknowledge them as the right way to do things.
So much of what we do at church is preference-based.
And if we allow it to become our prejudice, if we look at other churches who do things differently than we do,
if we look at other Christians who do things differently than we do,
and we make our preferences our prejudices,
we will end up despising people who God called us to sit at the same table.
And look, I have a heart, and this will not be easy,
and I don't even have a strategic plan for it.
I don't know that you can't have a strategic plan for it.
But I would love for our church to become more ethnically diverse in the future.
And if we're going to do that,
we better be sure we know what our preferences are.
And we better be willing to lay them down because so often churches attract the same type of person
because we build our ministry and our methodology around our preferences,
and we make our preferences our prejudices.
We've got to be willing to have an open hand about the type of songs we sing,
how often we sing the songs,
what happens during worship,
what doesn't happen during worship,
all of these things.
If we're going to welcome a diverse group of people,
we cannot make our preferences our prejudices.
Fourth, we seek to replace the ministry of the Holy Spirit.
Again, Paul says,
let God hold them up.
Let God deal with them.
You don't have to do his job for him.
See, we love the idea of doing God's job for him.
It's fun to, like, live it out,
but the responsibility is far too big for us to handle.
So, do not replace the Holy Spirit in somebody else's life.
Lastly, we prioritize winning an argument over winning a person.
We'd much rather just be right or convince ourselves that we're right
so we can sleep better at night
than winning a person,
which is the whole point of all of this.
People are the point.
Unity with one another is the point.
So, if we're going to have a church
that is successful at reaching a diverse group of people
and remains unified and effective,
we have to daily choose to accept one another
because God has accepted us
and not to judge one another over disputable matters
because God's going to judge all of us.
Don't hear me saying that you're not allowed to have opinions.
Lord knows I have opinions.
Lots of them.
Just come talk to me afterwards.
I will give you all of my opinions on all of the things.
Actually, I won't because I'm your pastor
and I don't want to cause you to stumble,
but I have them.
Believe me.
You can have your opinions,
but make sure your opinions are rooted in prayerful study of God's word
and a willingness to listen and submit to the Holy Spirit.
So many Christians who think they're strong,
think they're strong on an opinion
or only strong on that opinion
because they haven't even considered what God thinks about it.
They've just convinced themselves that they're good.
Of course I can do this.
Of course I can live this way.
Of course I can act this way.
Same thing on the weak, right?
The weaks.
There are people on weak side
who literally have just accepted some man's rules.
Some pastor told them,
here's the check boxes.
Here are the black and whites.
And you just say,
yeah, that's got to be right.
Whichever side you're on,
please make sure that your opinions are rooted in God's word.
Listening to the Holy Spirit.
God, is this what you would have for me to do?
Is this how you would have me to live?
And then once you form those opinions in that way,
bring them with an open hand
to a brother or sister who doesn't agree with you.
Have a beneficial conversation.
Have a meaningful conversation with a brother or sister
who disagrees with you on a disputable issue
and do so with honor.
And you might just find that God uses you
to change their mind.
Or God forbid he might use them to change your mind.
But the worst case scenario
in that hypothetical
is you both walk away loving God
and loving each other more
in the midst of your disagreement.
And that, my friends,
is Paul's entire point.
Chapter 14 and 15.
He wraps up,
we didn't go through the whole text,
but he wraps up his argument.
He starts it in 14.1
and he finishes it in 15.7,
which he says,
therefore, welcome one another
as Christ has welcomed you
for the glory of God.
This is the point.
We'd sit around the same table
looking to Jesus at the head,
looking to one another
in the midst of our disagreements.
Disunity grieves the heart of God
and it renders the church
ineffective of our mission.
May we prioritize unity
in the midst of diversity.
May we have our opinions
in open hands.
I think we're,
pastoral, I'll just say,
I think we're relatively okay
at this here,
but man, may we not lose sight of it.
And may we not have blind spots
or think, get comfortable with this.
If you're in here
and you're not a follower of Jesus,
I hope that what you heard today
was that God designed his church
to be the most welcoming,
diverse, and unified place on earth.
And we have not lived up
to our end of the bargain.
Don't hold that against him.
See so many people
who refuse to even consider
the claims of Jesus
because of the failures of the church.
If you're in here
and if you're struggling
with Christianity
because you see the way
Christians living out the faith,
do not hold our actions against him.
Consider his words.
Consider his invitation
to be welcomed to this family,
diverse and unified people.
Submit to him as Lord.
Bring your strengths
into our community
and help us live out
his desire for his church.
Welcome one another
as Christ has welcomed you
for the glory of God.
Let's pray.
Father,
we are so grateful
that you have set a table
in the presence of our enemies.
That you sit at the head
of that table
and you invite
male and female,
slave and free,
Jew and Gentile,
Democrat and Republican.
You invite a diverse group
of people
from a diverse group
of backgrounds
all on the one,
on the singular basis
that we're willing
to bow our knee
to you as Lord.
And if we're really willing
to do that,
everything else
will take care of itself.
God, may we be a people
who come to that table
laying down our opinions,
our preferences,
bowing our knee
to Jesus as Lord
whose rules
and regulations
are love the Lord your God
with all of your heart,
soul, mind, and strength
and love your neighbor
as yourself.
God, if we do that well,
I know that unity will happen.
God, may we be a diverse
and unified body
that the world around us
looks in and sees
and says something is different
about those people.
They're able to have
hard conversations
with dignity
and with respect.
They're able to lock arms
with brothers and sisters
who don't look like them,
talk like them,
vote like them,
believe certain things
that they believe.
And yet,
they find unity
because of their love
for this Jesus.
God, may we be an effective,
unified church
for your glory.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.